Leslie Nelson Savage Mahoney Papers, 1880-1986
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Leslie Nelson Savage Mahoney papers
1890-1986
1942-1970
Mahoney, Leslie Nell Savage, 1890-1986
MS 229
10 boxes (4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Architectural historian and interior decorator. The papers provide insight into the life a southern woman and a professional single mother. Her writings include material related to interior decorating; poetry; travel diaries; an unpublished biography of her father; and photographs of mostly family mambers. Correspondents include photographer, Frances Benjamin Johnston and lawyer and House of Representatives member, Lucy Sommerville Howorth.
Leslie Nelson ("Nell") Savage was born in 1890 in Nashville, Tennessee, one of three daughters of Leslie Alice Jones and opthamologist Dr. Giles Christopher Savage. She graduated from Ward Seminary, a private girls' school in Nashville, in 1908 and began study at Vanderbilt University. After a year she transferred to Goucher College in Baltimore, Maryland, receiving a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1912. Her continued interest in architectural history and design led her to take courses at the Art League in New York, the New York School of Applied Design for Women, and Cooper Union. She began study in 1916 at Ward Belmont School, completing a Certificate in Interior Decorating. In July 1918, she received an appointment as clerk in the Surgeon General's Office in Washington, D.C. She resigned in October of the same year. In 1923 she married Charles Hallum Mahoney, the first cousin of her sister Kate's husband. They were divorced in May 1925. She received full custody of their daughter Margaret Ellerbe Mahoney who was born in October 1924.
Nell entered Vanderbilt University in 1937 and received her Master of Arts degree in history in 1939. Her thesis was titled "The Building of the Tennessee State House, 1845-1854," and was written under the direction of Professor Frank L. Owsley. She worked as an interior decorator, lecturer, and writer. Her work on architect William Strickland was published in the Tennessee Historical Quarterly and various magazines and newspapers. In 1944, she worked for the Department of Military Intelligence in the Signal Corps. Although she anticipated the publication of a monograph on Strickland through McMillan & Co., the manuscript was never completed. She died January 30, 1986.
The Leslie Nelson Savage Mahoney Papers consist of four linear feet of correspondence, writings, diaries, and photographs and date from 1890 to 1986. The bulk of the material dates from 1942 to 1970. The papers are both personal and professional in nature and provide insight into the life a southern woman and a professional single mother.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
IV. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open according to the rules of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Leslie Nelson Savage Mahoney Papers were received from the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, where they were temporarily stored, in three installments between 1986 and 1988. Additional materials were received with the Margaret E. Mahoney papers donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in the same period.
Search Terms
Cisneros, Eleanora de, 1978-1934--Photographs; Howorth, Lucy Sommerville, 1885- --Correspondence; Johnston, Frances Benjamin, 1864-1952--Correspondence; Mahoney, Leslie Nell Savage, 1890-1986; Mahoney, Margaret, 1924-; Thumb, Tom, 1838-1883--Photographs; Divorced mothers--United States--History--20th century; Interior decorators--United States--History--20th century; Southern States--Social life and customs--20th century; Tennessee--Architecture--Nashville--History--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the Margaret E. Mahoney papers in the Sophia Smith Collection, the Tenessee State Library Archives, and the Interior Design Department, Watkins College of Art Design in Nashville, Tennessee.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1893-1986; 1.75 linear ft.
  This series contains a handwritten autobiography which describes Nell Mahoney's life to 1923 and a biographical sketch written by her friend, Dorothy Saunders. There are a series of personal diaries (1933-45, 1952, 1962-69) from Nashville and Monteagle, Tennessee; travel diaries from Europe (1906, 1960s) and engagement calendars (1966, 1969, 1979). There are also miscellaneous biographical items on Giles Christopher and Alice Leslie Savage as well as Nell Savage Mahoney. These includes legal documents such as wills and Nell's divorce decree. This series also contains memorabilia consisting of school records and a scrapbook. The scrapbook which contained clippings, memorabilia, and photographs has been photocopied and dismantled.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1902-72; 1.75 linear ft.
  This series is organized into two subseries: Personal and Business. The Personal subseries is divided into two sections, incoming and outgoing. The first section contains personal correspondence from friends and family. Correspondents include photographer, Frances Benjamin Johnston (1934-42), and lawyer and House of Representatives member, Lucy Sommerville Howorth (1953-72). There are also significant runs of letters from her mother (1902-54) and her friends, Virginia Polk (1951-72), operator with her husband of the largest Mississippi plantation system, and Elizabeth Rogers (1939-69), history professor at Wilson College. The second section contains letters to her daughter, Margaret E. Mahoney (1940s, 1960s), her mother, Leslie Alice Savage (1935-52), and her sister, Kate Savage Zerfoss (1939-47). Letters from her daughter are contained in the Margaret E. Mahoney Papers and are closed until 2015. The Business correspondence includes material related to her research on architect William Strickland.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, 1933-69; .5 linear ft.
  This series consists of typescripts and notes related to Nell Mahoney's interior decorating work, poems, a biography of her father, and a series of newspaper articles from the Nashville Tenneseean on Nashville history art and architecture, 1949-53.
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS, 1880-1984; 2.5 linear in.
  There are circa 110 photographs in this series dating from 1880 to 1986. These include photographs of Nell, her parents, and other family members. There are miscellaneous photos including Tom Thumb and his wife, singer Eleonora de Cisneros, and Frances Benjamin Johnston. [See also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL--Scrapbook]
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1893-1986
  - General 1942-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaries
    - Nashville and Monteagle, Tennessee
      - 1933-1945, 1952, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1a-17)
      - 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Europe, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rome, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Paris, post 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - England, 1968? (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Engagement calendars, 1966, 1969, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - "Nell Savage Mahoney, July 16, 1890 to January 30, 1986" by Dorothy Saunders, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous documents and clippings, 1890-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Memorabilia
    - School records
      - Ward Seminary
        - Miscellaneous, 1908-10 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Yearbook, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - History of art notebook, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Goucher College, 1909-12, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Ward-Belmont School, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Vanderbilt University, 1910-67 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1910-17
    - Photocopy (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Contents (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1902-72
  - Personal
    - Incoming
      - Edward and Florence Ardery, 1914-56, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Joseph Albert Bennet, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Jean Bradford, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Paul Bragrams, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Susan Clark Carr, 1965-71 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Christopher and Linda Clark, 1966-71 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Portia Ward Clark, 1965-71, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Nannie Dudley, 1941, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Bess Eager, 1965-70 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Helen Einwalter, 1965-71, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Irene Agnes Eweret, 1941-44 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Ruth Anna Fisher, 1953-65 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Marguerite Fry, 1969-70, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Valerie Graham, 1967-70, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Dina Harris, 1942-44, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Mary Park Heym, 1953-71 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Lucy Howorth, 1953-72 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Rick Johanson, 1968-70 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Marjorie Johanson, 1967-70 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - May Johanson (cousin), 1912, 1952-56, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Eunice Jones, 1965-69 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Frances Benjamin Johnston, 1934-42 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Lt. Tom M. Kelly, 1944-45 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - Mary Kirby-Smith, 1966-71 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Cynthia Anne McMillan, 1969-70 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Walter A. Montgomery, 1944-45 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Rebecca T. Nelson, 1954-72, undated (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
      - John and Muriel Pilley, 1941-49 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Virginia Polk, 1951-72, undated (Box 6, Folder 7-10)
      - Elizabeth Rogers, 1939-70, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - William Sattler1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 2a)
      - Dorothy and Lawrence Saunders, 1932, 1944-70, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Leslie Savage (mother), 1902, 1939-44, 1950-54 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Nellie Nugent Sommerville, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Cary Eleanor Waples, 1935-64, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Eleanor Woodward, 1965-68 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Laura Hunter Wyatt-Brown, 1954-68, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Kate Zerfoss (sister) and family, 1941-55, 1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - A-K, 1935-69, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - L-Z, 1917-69, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Unidentified, 1940-71, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Wedding announcements and invitations, 1919-54 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Outgoing
      - Christopher and Linda Clark, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Margaret Ellerbe Mahoney (daughter), 1940-65 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Alice Leslie Savage (mother), 1935-52 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Kate Zerfoss (sister), 1939, 1944, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Business
    - A-W, 1940-69, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Arthur Vernay Co., 1934-36 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - William Wright Crandall, 1940-44 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - War service, 1918, 1944-46 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lectures, 1927, 1934-37, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Arts Club of Washington, 1918, 1947-55 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - British Museum and Library of Congress1938-1956 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Country Life1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Carnegie Coporation of New York1936-1938 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Julius Rosenwald Fund1941 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - The Macmillan Company1944-1955 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1952-56, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous organizations, 1936-37, 1953-55 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Third party: Kelly Graham
    - Cain, Stewart (?) Hall1943 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano1936 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, 1933-69
  - "Account of Giles Christopher Savage," undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Poems for Margaret E. Mahoney, 1937, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Poems, 1953, 1968-1977, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Worksheet of a Decorator," 1933-37 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Research notes, 1951-69 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Articles from the Nashville Tennessean, 1949-53 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS, 1880-1984
  - Giles Christopher Savage, 1880-1925, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Leslie Alice Savage, 1886-1909, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Fanny D. and Anson Nelson (grandparents), 1898 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Nell Savage Mahoney
    - Alone, circa 1891-1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - With family, circa 1892-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Family, 1905-41 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1918, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)